Guide to Philosophy Talk SC1118
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
- Program audio, 2002-2018
  - Persons, Selves, Souls, and Loops, 2008 Jan 20; 1 computer file(s) (mp3)
    Can a self, a consciousness, an "I" arise out of mere matter? If it cannot, then how can you or I be here? And if it can, how does THAT work? These and other questions of identity are central to I Am A Strange Loop, the latest book by Indiana University Philosopher Douglas Hofstadter, author of the acclaimed Godel, Escher, Bach. He joins John and Ken for a probing discussion of the self, the soul, and the strange loop that binds them.
  - St. Augustine, 2008 Jan 27; 1 computer file(s) (mp3)
    The philosopher Saint Augustine of Hippo is one of the most important figures in the history of Christianity. His efforts against the Manichean, Arian and Pelagain heresies shaped the fundamentals of Christian doctrine. His Confessions tells the story of his own conversion from Manicheanism to Christianity. His philosophical ideas anticipated Saint Thomas Aquinas and Descartes. His three-volume City of God remains a classic of Christian apologetics. And many find the roots of some of the darker sides of Christian doctrine, from the emphasis on original sin to the second-rate status for women, in his works. John and Ken welcome Georgetown University Provost James O'Donnell, author of Augustine, Sinner & Saint: A New Biography.
  - Paradoxes, 2008 Feb 3; 1 computer file(s) (mp3)
    A paradox is a persuasive argument that something, which we judge must be false, is true. Zeno's Paradox, for example, is a convincing argument that it's impossible to move. Paradoxes are valuable in philosophy because they help us become aware of forms of argument that are deceptively convincing yet logically fallacious. John and Ken are joined by Roy Sorensen from Dartmouth College, author of A Brief History of the Paradox, to consider what we can learn from paradoxes.
  - Connectionism, 2008 Feb 17; 1 computer file(s) (mp3)
    Does the human mind work like a computer? If so, what kind of computer? A theory known as connectionism offers a revolutionary perspective on these issues. Ken and John delve into cutting-edge cognitive science with Jay McClelland from Stanford University, an architect of the connectionist view.
  - Infinity, 2008 Feb 24; 1 computer file(s) (mp3)
    Infinity is a puzzling concept. Mathematicians say there are as many odd numbers as there are numbers altogether. That seems like saying there are as many men as there are people altogether which we know is untrue. And if you subtract infinity from infinity, you are still left with infinity but which infinity? Some infinities are larger than others how can this be? John and Ken unravel the paradoxes of infinity with Rudy Rucker, Professor Emeritus of Computer Science at San Jose State University and author of Infinity and the Mind: The Science and Philosophy of the Infinite.
  - Science vs. Pseudo-science, 2008 Mar 2; 1 computer file(s) (mp3)
    Astronomy is science; Astrology is pseudo-science. Evolutionary Biology is science; Creationism is pseudo-science. How about cultural anthropology, abstract economics, string-theory, and evolutionary psychology science or pseudo-science? Is pseudo-science just politically incorrect science? Or is there an objective difference? John and Ken tackle these questions with Stuart Vyse from Connecticut College, author of Believing in Magic: The Psychology of Superstition.
  - Apologizing, 2008 Mar 30; 1 computer file(s) (mp3)
    Can you be sorry without intending to change your behavior in the future? Without being ashamed? Do other cultures have different concepts of sorrow and guilt? John and Ken unapologetically explore the language and philosophy of contrition with Nick Smith from the University of New Hampshire, author of I Was Wrong: The Meanings of Apologies.
  - Philosophy of Wine, 2008 Apr 6; 1 computer file(s) (mp3)
    The discriminating wine palate: bouquet, nose, great vintages, genius vintners. Are these just myths perpetrated by winemakers and taken up by snobs with too much money to spend? John and Ken raise a philosophical glass with Barry Smith from the University of London, editor of Questions of Taste: The Philosophy of Wine.
  - Politics and Cognitive Science, 2008 Apr 13; 1 computer file(s) (mp3)
    Can cognitive science explain the difference between liberals and conservatives? Do we elect our presidents on the basis of stale metaphors and the manipulations of pernicious language mavens? We put these questions to George Lakoff, Professor of Linguistics at UC Berkeley and author of Thinking Points: Communicating Our American Values and Vision.
  - Varieties of Love, 2008 Apr 20; 1 computer file(s) (mp3)
    Is love a single thing, or just a word we use to express any number of unrelated emotions? Is love intrinsically irrational? What have philosophers said about love? Did they know what they were talking about? Christopher Phillips, author of Socrates in Love, joins John and Ken for a program recorded live at Powell's City of Books in Portland, Oregon.
  - Experimental Philosophy, 2008 May 4; 1 computer file(s) (mp3)
    Philosophical reasoning relies on intuitions. John Rawls called this method "reflective equilibrium.  But where do we get our data about "intuitions"? John and Ken welcome back Anthony Appiah from Princeton University, author of Experiments in Ethics. They discuss psychological experiments that determine what people really think.
  - Promises, 2008 May 11; 1 computer file(s) (mp3)
    What is a promise: a prediction? A statement of intention? Is promising rational? Does it create an obligation? John and Ken promise to raise these issues and more with Sir Neil MacCormick from the University of Edinburgh, author of Rhetoric and the Rule of Law.
  - Summer Reading List 2008, 2008 Jun 1; 1 computer file(s) (mp3)
    Summer's just around the corner what books are you going to pack with your Speedo? John and Ken leaf through some of this summer's philosophy, fiction, and non-fiction reading with Danielle Marshall from Powell's City of Books.
  - The Problem of Evil, 2008 Jun 8; 1 computer file(s) (mp3)
    Many religions tell us that God is perfect: all-knowing, all-powerful, and beneficent. Why then do bad things happen? John and Ken discuss the problem of evil with their guest, Michael Tooley from the University of Colorado at Boulder, co-author of Knowledge of God.
  - Hannah Arendt, 2008 Jun 22; 1 computer file(s) (mp3)
    Hannah Arendt was one of the most original and influential philosophers of the 20th century. Her work considered historical and contemporary political events, such as the rise and fall of Nazism, and drew conclusions about the relation between the individual and society. Seyla Benhabib,Professor of Political Science and Philosophy at Yale University and Director of its Program in Ethics, Politics and Economics, joins John and Ken discuss Arendt's political philosophy and its enduring influence.
  - Altruism, 2008 Jun 29; 1 computer file(s) (mp3)
    Are people genuinely altruistic, or is altruism just a type of selfish-behavior? Are other animals altruistic? Should we strive to be altruistic, or is selfishness a higher virtue? John and Ken take the moral high ground with their guest Jeff Schloss, Professor and Chair of Biology at Westmont College and co-editor of Altruism and Altruistic Love: Science, Philosophy, and Religion in Dialogue.
  - The Luck of the Draw, 2008 Jul 13; 1 computer file(s) (mp3)
    Sometimes it isn't possible to distribute goods evenly. When this happens, we often leave it up to randomness in the form of lotteries to decide who gets what. Is this just? Or is it merely the best we can do? What distinguishes fair systems of randomization from unfair ones? John and Ken take their chances with Peter Stone, Assistant Professor of Political Science at Stanford University.
  - Giving and Keeping, 2008 Jul 27; 1 computer file(s) (mp3)
    How should people allocate their assets however modest or grand ethically and effectively? What kinds of giving should the government encourage through tax incentives and other measures? Is providing for loved ones more worthy than self-expression through philanthropy? John and Ken are joined by Rob Reich, Associate Professor of Political Science and Ethics in Society at Stanford University, for a program recorded before a live audience at the Classic Residence by Hyatt in Palo Alto, CA
  - Philosophy and Pop Culture, 2008 Aug 3; 1 computer file(s) (mp3)
    From Star Trek and the Grateful Dead to South Park and Stephen Colbert, philosophical questions are everywhere in popular culture: Is time travel possible? Can a person survive being disintegrated and reassembled? Does humor enable the expression of deep truths, political or otherwise? John and Ken look at the Big Questions in pop culture with Richard Hanley from the University of Delaware, author of South Park and Philosophy. This program was recorded before a live audience at the University of Delaware in Newark, DE.
  - Dualism, 2008 Aug 10; 1 computer file(s) (mp3)
    What is the relationship between the mind and the brain? Monists believe that there is only one substance or property in the Universe, be it physical (Materialists) or mental (Idealists). But Dualists, like the 17th Century French philosopher Rene Descartes, hold that mental stuff exists side by side with physical stuff. Can this view be defended, in light of modern science? John and Ken probe the mind-body with David Rosenthal from City University of New York, author of Consciousness and Mind.
  - Global Justice and Human Rights, 2008 Aug 24; 1 computer file(s) (mp3)
    What constitutes a just society? What are the obligations of liberal democracies to ensure the rights and well-being of the citizens of other countries? What kinds of interventions and institutions are most suitable to the task of preventing war, disease, and poverty in the world today? John and Ken discuss the requirements of justice with Helen Stacy from Stanford Law School.
  - Utilitarianism, 2008 Sep 7; 1 computer file(s) (mp3)
    Can morality be quantified? Can the good be calculated? Utilitarianism says the right action is the one which leads to the most overall happiness - a deceptively simple theory, but not without its detractors. Is utilitarianism compatible with the idea that people have inalienable rights? Should we be so focused on the consequences of our actions? John and Ken welcome Wayne Sumner from the University of Toronto, author of The Hateful and the Obscene: Studies in the Limits of Free Expression.
  - The Morality of Food, 2008 Sep 21; 1 computer file(s) (mp3)
    Veganism, freeganism, organic, sustainability, simplicity, biofuel, animal rights, worker's rights, nutrition, preventing hunger, reducing waste and protecting the environment. What obligations do we have when it comes to buying, eating and producing food? How should we balance moral and practical concerns? John and Ken chew on these questions with Michael Pollan from the UC Berkeley School of Journalism, author of The Omnivore's Dilemma and In Defense of Food.
  - Overcoming the Terror of Death, 2008 Oct 12; 1 computer file(s) (mp3)
    To many death is terrifying. But why? As David Hume pointed out, all the years we didn't exist before we were born seemed painless enough. Why worry about future non-existence? Is the real worry that we will continue to exist? Ken and John confront mortality with psychiatrist and novelist Irv Yalom, author of Staring at the Sun: Overcoming the Terror of Death. This program was recorded before a live audience at The Marsh theater in San Francisco.
  - Digital Selves, 2008 Oct 19; 1 computer file(s) (mp3)
    Second Life and dozens of other online adventures involve creating digital selves, and millions of users are taking advantage of the opportunity to develop new personas. Cyberpunk literature, like William Gibson's Neuromancer, describes worlds in which the line between digital selves and real selves is hard to draw. What makes your digital self you? What does your choice of digital selves show about you? And what makes onscreen representation more or less effective as digital selves? John and Ken are joined by Jeremy Bailenson, Director of Stanford's Virtual Human Interaction Lab, for a program recorded before a live audience at The Marsh theater in San Francisco.
  - Making Decisions, 2008 Nov 2; 1 computer file(s) (mp3)
    When we make decisions we think we're in control, making rational choices. But are we? This is the central question posed by Dan Ariely, Professor of Behavioral Economics at Duke University, in his book Predictably Irrational. Ken and John discuss irrationality, its dangers, and perhaps also its benefits, with this philosophical and fascinating economist.
  - William James, 2008 Nov 9; 1 computer file(s) (mp3)
    William James is a great figure, historically important as a philosopher (pragmatism and radical empiricism), a student of religion (author of the monumental Varieties of Religious Experience), and psychology. Ken and John examine the life and ideas of this towering figure with Russell Goodman, a leading scholar of Pragmatism and author of Wittgenstein and William James.
  - Gandhi, 2008 Nov 16; 1 computer file(s) (mp3)
    Gandhi is famous as the leader of the movement for Indian independence, which he based on his philosophy of non-violence, an important influence on Martin Luther King Jr. Gandhi's ideas and the effects of his leadership continue to influence the world and its leaders. What was the philosophical basis these ideas? Is non-violence a strategy for a certain purpose, or the basis for a way of life? Ken and John welcome Akeel Bilgrami, Director of the Heyman Center for the Humanities at Columbia University and author of "Gandhi, the Philosopher."
  - Levels of Reality, 2008 Nov 23; 1 computer file(s) (mp3)
    Are there levels of reality, with each level emerging from the other in a way that provides a truly new aspect of reality? The concept of emergence has been seen as an alternative to mere reducibility in discussion of the relation of the physical world to the biological world, consciousness, the social world, and God. Ken and John probe the nature of reality with Tim O'Connor, Professor of Philosophy at Indiana University and author of Theism and Ultimate Explanation.
  - Bodies For Sale, 2008 Dec 7; 1 computer file(s) (mp3)
    I can sell my house, the things I make, and the services I provide. So why can't I sell one of my kidneys? What is the philosophical basis for the taboo against selling parts of our bodies? There is an (illegal) market in body parts; shouldn't we trust the wisdom of the market and make it legitimate? Or would doing so undermine the very dignity of persons and human life? Ken and John dissect the issues with Stanford Philosopher Debra Satz, author of Why Some Things Should Not Be for Sale: On The Limits of Markets.
  - John Rawls, 2008 Dec 14; 1 computer file(s) (mp3)
    John Rawls was one of the most influential political philosophers of the twentieth century. In his book A Theory of Justice he articulated a concept of justice as fairness, which won many fans among liberals, and provoked important responses from thoughtful libertarians such as Robert Nozick. Ken and John discuss the life and ideas of John Rawls with Joshua Cohen, Professor of Political Science, Philosophy, andLaw at Stanford University and co-author of Associations and Democracy.
  - The Idea of the University, 2009 Jan 4; 1 computer file(s) (mp3)
    Is a university a research institute with students, or and educational institution with research around the edges or something in between? To whom does the university answer the trustees? The administration? The faculty? The students? Or something more abstract, like knowledge and wisdom? John and Ken examine the very idea of a university with Stanford Provost John Etchemendy, in a program recorded before a live audience at the Annenberg Auditorium on the Stanford campus.
  - Philosophy of History, 2009 Jan 11; 1 computer file(s) (mp3)
    Is history just a series of events, or an interpretation of those events? Is there progress in history? Can history be objective, or is it, as Napoleon said, just the version of past events that people have decided to agree upon? Ken and John delve into the past and its meaning with Daniel Little, Chancellor of the University of Michigan-Dearborn and author of History's Pathways (forthcoming in March 2009) and Varieties of Social Explanation.
  - Civil Disobedience, 2009 Jan 18; 1 computer file(s) (mp3)
    Thoreau, Gandhi, and Martin Luther King all engaged in civil disobedience, and are widely admired for doing so. But how can democratic society function if each person's conscience has to be satisfied for a law to be obeyed? When is civil disobedience justified? When is it required? How does the concept fit with the great ethical and political philosophies? John and Ken discuss the ethics of protest and punishment with Kimberley Brownlee from the University of Manchester.
  - Creativity, 2009 Jan 25; 1 computer file(s) (mp3)
    What makes an idea or work of art creative? Can creativity be measured? Can a computer be creative? What is the relationship between creativity and consciousness? John and Ken explore their creative sides with Margaret Boden from the University of Sussex, author of The Creative Mind: Myths and Mechanisms.
  - Movie Show, 2009 Feb 2; 1 computer file(s) (mp3)
  - Different Cultures, Different Selves, 2009 Feb 22; 1 computer file(s) (mp3)
    Why do we do what we do? To please others? To live up to what culture expects? Or for our own reasons as "autonomous agents"? Americans tend to admire (at least in theory) the autonomous individual, the person who knows what he wants, and sets out to get it, no matter what the world might think. Is this true of all cultures? John and Ken are joined by Stanford Psychologist Hazel Markus to explore differences in motivation and action across cultures.
  - Bi-racial Identities, 2009 Mar 1; 1 computer file(s) (mp3)
    Many people identify strongly with the ethnic or racial group to which they belong as Jews, or African-Americans, or Latinos. But to which groups does a person truly belong? President Obama has a white mother from Kansas and an African father from Kenya. Why is he seen as our first African-American President, rather than our forty-fourth white president? How does racial identity work? Is such identification a positive or a negative factor in a person's life? Must we choose among our potential identities? Ken and John discuss racial and bi-racial identity with Michele Elam from Stanford University, author of Mixed Race in the New Millennium (forthcoming from Stanford University Press in 2009) and Race, Work, and Desire in American Literature, 1860-1930.
  - Challenges to Free Will, 2009 Mar 8; 1 computer file(s) (mp3)
    We seem to be able to decide our behavior for ourselves what we do is up to us. But if everything that we do can be explained by physics, does this leave room for freedom? Are all of our actions pre-determined? Are we slaves to fate? Is freedom compatible with determinism, or does science teach us that we're nothing but complex machines, following out a complicated program that a good enough physicist could have predicted centuries ago? And what are the implications for morality and responsibility? John and Ken exercise their will with Manuel Vargas from the University of San Francisco.
  - The Copyright Wars, 2009 Mar 22; 1 computer file(s) (mp3)
    Today there is an entire generation of people who have never paid for music. From Napster to YouTube, some of our most innovative and inventive young people have been the targets of lawsuits by entertainment industry lawyers for violating copyright laws. What are the ideas behind copyright protection? What is the philosophical and practical basis of copyright? Can rethinking the issues suggest the form of a truce between generations? Ken and John sample the copyright debate with Larry Lessig, author of Remix: Making Art and Commerce Thrive in the Hybrid Economy.
  - The Root of All Evil?, 2009 Mar 29; 1 computer file(s) (mp3)
    Money makes the world go around. But what sort of thing is money? Bits of paper and metal? An elaborate set of IOUs to be redeemed with more IOUs? An abstract accounting tool? If money is real, how can billions disappear on the stock market? And where does it go? Ken and John follow the money its nature, its utility, and whether it is the root of all evil with Stanford Economist Alex Gould.
  - Too Much Information, 2009 Apr 5; 1 computer file(s) (mp3)
    We re just never going to catch up,  writes David Weinberger in Everything Is Miscellaneous. That is, we're never going to catch up with the flood of information that is thrown at us by modern technology, especially the internet. We can never get all of our email filed, our digital pictures labeled, our calendars updated, our computers organized. Is the problem too much information, or out-of-date expectations about how information should be organized? Ken and John try to make sense of the flood of information with author and philosopher David Weinberger.
  - Desire, 2009 Apr 12; 1 computer file(s) (mp3)
    There are two ways to have your desires fulfilled: you can either get what you want (if you're lucky enough) or change your desires. If we can fit our desires to what we have, we're likely to be a lot happier. So why do we desire things that are out of reach? Why do we have desires that make us unhappy? And what can we do about it? John and Ken explore the relationship between desire and happiness with William Irvine, author of On Desire: Why We Want What We Want, in a program recorded before a live audience at the Illahee Institute in Portland, Oregon.
  - Beliefs Gone Wild, 2009 May 3; 1 computer file(s) (mp3)
    Our brains evolved on the African savannah, but are now expected to deal with complex statistical information and other intricate concepts every day. The result: beliefs gone wild. Ken and John reveal the traps that the mismatch between our brains and the world we live in pose for ordinary mortals with their guest, The Undercover Philosopher, Michael Philips. This program was recorded before a live audience at the Illahee Institute in Portland, Oregon.
  - Worship, 2009 May 10; 1 computer file(s) (mp3)
    Worship is the feeling or expression of reverence and adoration for something. The attitude of worship towards God or gods or ancestors is a universal of human culture. But why do we worship? Do objects of worship need to fulfill certain criteria? Does worship play a positive or negative role in human culture? Is it clear that a perfect, omnipotent and omniscient God truly wants to be worshipped? Some pagan religions worship the earth, or the aspects of nature that make human life possible and rewarding. Does this make more sense than worshipping an imperfect God? The Philosophers express their reverence with Daniel Speak from Loyola Marymount University.
  - Lincoln, 2009 May 17; 1 computer file(s) (mp3)
    More than any other President, Abraham Lincoln is known for his words, from the Lincoln-Douglass debates to the second inaugural address, as well as his deeds. What was Lincoln's basic philosophy, and did it change over the course of his Presidency? Ken and John welcome back Chicago Public Radio's Resident Philosopher, Al Gini, to celebrate the bicentennial of Lincoln, the man and his ideas.
  - The Mind and the World, 2009 Jun 7; 1 computer file(s) (mp3)